The age of menopause is only
partly determined by genetics.
So, what about the
influence of lifestyle factors?
Watch the video to find out.
"How to Delay the Age of Menopause
with Diet and Lifestyle Factors"
Since 1970,
the proportion of women having
their first child after age 35
increased nearly tenfold.
This may introduce a "longevity
penalty" on their children,
as those born to older mothers
don't tend to live as long,
but mothers
having children later
tend to live longer themselves.
For example,
female centenarians
were found to be
nearly four times more likely
to have had children
after age 40
than women
who died by their 70s.
This doesn't necessarily mean
delaying kids
will make you live longer.
Smoking, for example,
could be a confounder,
causing both early menopause
and an early death.
Or maybe
delayed reproductive aging
is just a sign
of slower aging in general.
However some have suggested the
biological changes of pregnancy
might have
a rejuvenating effect,
even going so far as to suggest
that parabiosis mechanism,
bathing in the blood of babies,
but just not in
a Countess Bathory sort of way.
To sort between
these possibilities,
researchers studied
the longevity
of brothers of women
who gave birth after age 45,
and that of their wives.
The brothers with late-fertile
sisters lived longer,
but their wives did not.
This suggests
a genetic robustness cause,
rather than
a rejuvenation effect,
and the fact
that the longevity benefit
didn't extend to their wives
suggests it's not due
to a confounder
like socioeconomic strata.
On the other hand,
women who experience
extremely early menopause,
the 1% who stop menstruating
by age 39,
may be at risk
for diminished longevity,
and should
therefore be counseled
to adopt a particularly
healthy diet and lifestyle.
Approximately half
of the variability
of age of menopause
between women
is explained by genetics.
Other than smoking,
what other behaviors
or circumstances
can help explain the rest?
Factors that don't appear
to affect the age of menopause
include exercise, obesity,
alcohol, coffee,
or vitamin D status.
Interestingly,
women who've been married
tend to arrive
at menopause later.
Some suggested it may be the
influence of male pheromones,
given the fact that exposure
to male armpit odor
makes women's cycles
more regular,
but it turns out
that male cohabitation alone
doesn't appear to matter.
It may be the sex.
Married older individuals tend
to have more sex, and indeed,
pre- and peri-menopausal women,
average age 46,
who reported sex weekly
were 28% less likely
to experience menopause
over the subsequent decade
than those reporting sex
less than once a month.
You can very well imagine
how this could be a result
of reverse causation, though.
Instead of more sex
leading to later menopause,
a later menopause
may have instead led
to more sexual engagement.
The relationship between
tobacco use and early menopause
is thought to be mediated
by the toxic effects
on the ovaries
of the polycyclic aromatic
hydrocarbons in the smoke.
Among nonsmokers,
this PAH exposure
is almost entirely from food,
mostly grilled, barbequed,
and smoked meats.
Could this explain why,
in the Harvard Nurses'
Health Study II,
higher plant protein intake
was associated
with a significantly lower risk
of early menopause?
Feed female monkeys
a diet high in animal protein
and not only did they get
more atherosclerosis,
but also an acceleration
of ovarian aging.
Now, in the original
Harvard Nurses' Health Study,
animal protein consumption
was associated with infertility,
such that replacing even 5%
of animal protein intake
with plant protein
could potentially cut the risk
of infertility in half.
But in
the Nurses' Health Study II,
while plant protein
appeared to delay menopause,
animal protein intake
was not associated
with menopause age
either way.
And in
the UK Women's Cohort Study,
those eating more animal protein
were 6% more likely
to experience a later menopause.
The data is similarly
conflicting in vegetarians.
Some studies
found no difference
or a later age of menopause
in vegetarians,
but others found an earlier age
compared to nonvegetarians.
For example,
the largest study
found that vegetarians
reached menopause
at an average age
of 50.1 years
compared to nonvegetarians
at 50.7 years.
As I noted, premature menopause
before age 40
may be detrimental
for longevity,
but being a little earlier
within the normal range
may actually be beneficial
for cancer risk.
At the same age, breast cancer
risk is about 40% higher
in premenopausal compared
to postmenopausal women,
presumably due
to higher exposure
to the "necessary evil"
hormone estrogen.
Breast cancer risk
is 3% higher
for every year later
a woman starts menopause
and 5% higher
for every year earlier
a girl starts menstruating.
On average, women whose periods
hold off until age 15
appear to live the longest.
Vegetarian women tend to have
lower estrogen levels,
perhaps due
to higher fiber intake,
and interventional studies show
that switching
to a more plant-based diet
can reduce
circulating estrogen levels
by more than 40%.
This could explain
why vegetarian girls
may hit puberty later,
and why those eating
strictly vegetarian
not only have
lower cancer risk overall,
but particularly lower risk
for female-specific cancers.
Age of menopause
may not be a factor though,
based on
an interventional trial
randomizing women
on the verge of menopause,
average age 49,
to two years
of a lower fat diet
to reduce breast cancer risk.
The intervention group
ended up eating more fiber,
and therefore more plant-based,
but though they did
experience improvements
in mammogram findings,
the dietary shift
failed to influence
the timing of menopause.